<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="rosco@[nospam].roscopeco.co.uk">Ross Bamford</author>
    <title>Jen Tools - Overview</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Jen Tools - Overview">
      <p>The optional <strong>Jen Tools</strong> library provides a number of Jen-based implementations
      of common classworking tools, such as <em>dynamic proxies</em> and <em>mock implementations</em>.
      Although all of the major features of the tools library can be found elsewhere, in all cases Jen
      is able to provide an advantage in terms of integration and flexibility passed on from the
      underlying <code>SoftClass</code> API. As with everything else in Jen, the driving force behind
      the tools API design is a careful balance of performance, flexibility, and ease of use, 
      with the result that a very wide range of requirements can be catered for in a very intuitive way.</p>

      <p><strong>Note</strong> that the tools library is on a slightly different version schedule
      to the core, since it was introduced at 0.20. New features will continue to be added to the
      library throughout alpha development, with a more focused testing policy to cover this flux.
      As a result of this there may be small changes in the public interface from version to version
      to accomodate added features as well as fixes.</p>

      <p>There follows a general description of the main features provided by the tools library,
      together with links to further API contract and user documentation in the 
      <a href='/nonav/docs/multiproject/jen-tools/apidocs/index.html'>Javadoc</a> and on the 
      <a href='http://wiki.java.net/bin/view/Javatools/JenDocTools'>wiki</a> respectively.</p>

      <subsection name="Dynamic Proxies">
        <p>As you would expect, Jen provides support for <em>dynamic proxy</em> classes, arguably the
        most common use-case for runtime class generation. Like <a href='http://cglib.sf.net/' target='_blank'>Cglib's</a>
        <code>
        <a href='http://cglib.sourceforge.net/apidocs/net/sf/cglib/proxy/Proxy.html' target='_blank'>Proxy</a>
        </code> implementation, Jen's <code>
        <a href='/nonav/docs/multiproject/jen-tools/apidocs/jen/tools/SoftProxy.html' target='_blank'>SoftProxy</a></code> with
        the <code>
        <a href='/nonav/docs/multiproject/jen-tools/apidocs/jen/tools/DefaultInvokerStrategy.html' target='_blank'>DefaultInvokerStrategy
        </a></code> (see point one, below) generates proxy classes that are outwardly compatible with the Java(tm) 
        SE platform proxies (generated with 
        <code><a href='http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/lang/reflect/Proxy.html' target='_blank'>
        java.lang.reflect.Proxy</a></code>, in that method calls on the dynamic proxy are dispatched to a user-supplied <code>
        <a href='http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/lang/reflect/InvocationHandler.html' target='_blank'>
        InvocationHandler</a></code> instance to be handled in an application-dependent way. Beneath the surface, 
        however, Jen proxies have a number of features not present in the other implementations:</p>
  
        <ul>
            <li>As indicated above, <code>SoftProxy</code> uses an <em>invoker generation strategy</em> to
            create the instance-based invocation implementation of the generated proxy class. The default strategy
            provides the entire platform-compatible proxy implementation, but can be easily switched out with
            a custom implementation of the <code>
            <a href='/nonav/docs/multiproject/jen-tools/apidocs/jen/tools/InvokerGenerationStrategy.html' target='_blank'>
            InvokerGenerationStrategy</a></code> interface to provide absolutely any implementation for
            the instance initialization and proxy invocation methods that you need.
            </li>
            <p/>
            <li>The default strategy includes functionality similar to that provided by Cglib's separate <code>
            <a href='http://cglib.sourceforge.net/apidocs/net/sf/cglib/proxy/Enhancer.html' target='_blank'>Enhancer</a>
            </code>,
            and fully supports both abstract class / interface and concrete class proxies via the same API.
            You can happily mix a superclass with implemented interfaces, and what's more, you can easily
            and safely dispatch to the appropriate <code>super</code> method from your <code>InvocationHandler</code>
            with a single method call. This high level of compatibility with the platform helps to ensure that
            proxy-based code does not become fragile in the face of refactoring or a change of implementation.</li>
            <p/>
            <li>Since <code>SoftProxy</code> uses 
            <code><a href='/nonav/docs/multiproject/jen-core/apidocs/jen/SoftClass.html'>SoftClass</a></code> for proxy
            generation, as well as allowing proxy classes to be defined directly at runtime it supports 
            generation of a byte array corresponding to the proxy <code>.class</code>. This could be
            serialized to a file, or across the network, or used as the basis for further transformation,
            to provide improved performance and advanced customization for those really tricky problems.
            </li>
        </ul>
  
        <p>These advanced features, together with the platform compatibility and flexible ease of use of Jen's
        <code>SoftProxy</code>, allow Jen to provide a simpler, more productive development turnaround for
        proxy-based code. Consider the following short example, which demonstrates the technique of calling
        custom code before and after an original method (what a certain ill-fated 'implementation paradigm' 
        would term 'around advice'):</p>        

        <source>import java.lang.reflect.InvocationHandler;
import java.lang.reflect.Method;

import com.mycompany.app.complex.RefurbulationDevice;
import com.mycompany.app.complex.StaticRefurbulator;
import com.mycompany.app.complex.StaticRefurbulationDevice;

import static com.mycompany.coverage.InvocationCollector.markEnter;
import static com.mycompany.coverage.InvocationCollector.markExit;

import static jen.tools.SoftProxy.newProxyInstance;
import static jen.tools.Toolbox.invokeSuper;

public class Examples {
  /* Our invocation handler simply calls some static methods to log the invocation.
     A certain ill-fated design paradigm would term this example 'around advice'. */
  static class MyInvocationHandler implements InvocationHandler { 
    public Object invoke(Object proxy, Method method, Object[] args) throws Throwable {

      markEnter(proxy,method,args);
      Object ret = invokeSuper(proxy,method,args);
      markExit(proxy,method,ret);
      
      return ret;
    }
  }

  public static void main(String[] args) {
    RefurbulationDevice ref = newProxyInstance(StaticRefurbulationDevice.class,new MyInvocationHandler());
    StaticRefurbulator.refurbulate(ref);

    InvocationCollector.report(System.out);
  }
}</source>

      <p>As you can see from this code, <code>SoftProxy</code> is just as easy to use as other contemporary
      proxy implementations, and provides considerably enhanced functionality together with a more 
      convenient API (thanks largely to the new Java(tm) 5 language features).</p>  
      </subsection>
  
      <subsection name="Mock implementations">
        <p>Mock implementations (often referred to generally as <em>mock objects</em>) are another mainstay of
        dynamic class generation, and are in fact (in Jen at least) a special case of the <em>dynamic proxies</em>
        discussed above. At present Jen doesn't support the extended expectation-based invocation constraints 
        supported by, for example, JMock, but the basic mock handler design allows such support to be added
        easily in a future version (as is planned).</p>

        <p>The <code>
        <a href='/nonav/docs/multiproject/jen-tools/apidocs/jen/tools/MockProxyHandler.html' target='_blank'>
        MockProxyHandler</a></code> class provides the central mock facilties, and is implemented as an
        <code>InvocationHandler</code> implementation allowing it to be used with any of the platform-compatible
        mock implementations, Jen-based or otherwise. We must supply a list or array of <code>
        <a href='/nonav/docs/multiproject/jen-tools/apidocs/jen/tools/MockMethod.html' target='_blank'>
        MockMethod</a></code> instances, which are used to dispatch calls to the mock object's methods.
        </p>

        <p>Once a mock handler is instantiated, it can be passed to an appropriate proxy class constructor.
        The resulting proxy instance will examine the list of methods on each method invocation, and
        dispatch the invocation to the first <code>MockMethod</code> that indicates it can handle the
        call. Default <code>MockMethod</code> implementations are provided to test constraints on the
        proxy instance, method name, invocation arguments, and return type before invoking, and custom
        implementations can be easily inserted to customise behaviour of the invocation itself.</p>

        <p><code>MockProxyHandler</code> also provides static helper methods that wrap up the process
        of instantiating a handler and creating a proxy instance. The following code fragment demonstrates
        simple mock usage:</p>
        
        <source>import java.lang.reflect.InvocationHandler;
import java.lang.reflect.Method;

import com.mycompany.app.complex.RefurbulationDevice;
import com.mycompany.app.complex.StaticRefurbulator;

import jen.tools.MockMethod;
import jen.tools.StubMock;

import org.roscopeco.bloxx.juno.Constraint;

import static jen.tools.MockProxyHandler.*;
import static org.roscopeco.bloxx.juno.Constraints.*;

public class Examples02 {
  public static void reportFailure(String err) {
    System.err.println(" >>> ERROR - TEST FAILED: "+err);
    throw(new RuntimeException(err));
  }

  public static void main(String[] args) {
    RefurbulationDevice ref = newMockInstance(RefurbulationDevice.class, new MockMethod[] {

        new StubMock("invokeReticuloBlob",new Constraint[] { isEqual("output"), and(not(isEqual(5)),notNull()) },
            returnValue("57 Chevy")),

        new StubMock("invokeReticuloBlob",new Constraint[] { isEqual("input") },
            returnValue("62 Olds")),

        new StubMock("invokeReticuloBlobX2",new Constraint[] { isEqual("output"), isNull() },
            new InvocationHandler() { 
              public Object invoke(Object proxy, Method m, Object[] args) {
                reportFailure("FAILED - Cannot X2 with null spiroambulator!");
              }
            }
    });

    StaticRefurbulator.refurbulate(ref);
  }
}</source>

        <p>Of course, all the extra features available to vanilla Jen proxies are also available
        with the mock invocation handler, so the above example could just have easily been mocking
        a concrete class as an interface. Plus, if you do mock concrete classes you can use
        the <code>Toolbox.callSuper()</code> method to return a standard mock stub that will
        pass the invocation to the proxied method.</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Toolbox">
        <p>The <code>
        <a href='/nonav/docs/multiproject/jen-tools/apidocs/jen/tools/Toolbox.html' target='_blank'>
        Toolbox</a></code> class provides a variety of static helpers and utility methods that
        automate many common tasks when using the tools library. It's methods include:</p>

        <ul>
          <li>Type descriptor / Type / Class conversion.</li>
          <li>Primitive type / class conversion and boxing.</li>
          <li>Methods / language signature / descriptor conversion.</li>
          <li>Concrete proxy forward invocation (<code>invokeSuper</code>).</li>
          <li>Standard stubs for <code>StubMock</code> - return, throw, call super.</li>
        </ul>

        <p>As with much of the Jen API, the <code>Toolbox</code> methods are intended to be used with
        the J5 <code>import static</code> statement, though of course they can be imported and invoked
        in the 'traditional' way if you prefer.</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
