<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="rosco@roscopeco.REMOVE.co.uk">Ross Bamford</author>
    <title>Welcome to Juno</title>
  </properties>
  <head>
    <meta name="description" content="Juno is a simple lightweight constraints library."/>
    <meta name="description" content="contraints,constrain,unit,test,junit,java,free,open,source,download"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <section name="Welcome to Juno">

      <p><strong>Welcome to <strong>Juno</strong> - a simple, self-contained, 
      zero-dependency (optional JUnit dependency for unit test integration) library 
      that provides a simple API for working with constrained values, and a wide 
      variety of ready-made constraint classes. Juno does exactly what it says on 
      the tin, and was inspired by <a href='mailto:rosco@roscopeco.REMOVE.co.uk'>the author</a>
      growing tired of porting mock object libraries into the runtime classpath. No 
      additional libraries are required to use the basic constraints capabilities of
      Juno, although Juno does support optional integration with both 
      <a href='http://jmock.org/'>JMock</a> and <a href='http://picocontainer.codehaus.org'>
      PicoContainer</a> parameter constraints, as well as <a href='http://junit.org/'>JUnit</a>
      test integration.
      </strong></p> 
      
      <p>Juno provides a simple abstract <code>Constraint</code> class that defines the
	    basic behaviour required, and a number of standard implementations of this class
      that implement various common constraints such as <i>equals</i>, <i>between</i>,
      <i>smaller than</i>, and so on. These are complimented by a static utility class
	    that provides (especially with JDK5 <code>import static</code>) as a more
			expressive syntax for constraint definition. As well as this,
      Juno provides <strong>standard converters</strong> that allow Juno 
      constraints to be used as drop-in replacements for other constraints
      libraries out there. This means that Juno can be used as a 'lowest-common-denominator'
      when implementing custom constraints, and retains the flexibility of lightweight,
      go anywhere constraints-based assertions.</p> 

      <p>Juno is a lightweight, highly-focused component that was specifically designed
      to fulfil the following requirements:</p>

      <ul>
        <li><p>As a general-purpose object-oriented way to define and apply constraints
			  to values and objects in software, at build, test, and run time. Inline constraints
        can provide a powerful and sophisticated solution to all kinds of common problems,
        from parameter resolution and multiple conditional branching to subset selection
        and filtering.
        </p></li>

				<li><p>As a more expressive way to handle assertions in Unit Tests. By either
        subclassing the <code>JunoTestCase</code> rather than JUnit's regular <code>TestCase</code>,
        or alternatively importing the static <code>assertThat</code> method from 
        <code>JunoTestCase</code> alongside the <code>Constraints</code> methods (under
        JSE 5.0 or later) you can write code such as:</p>

        <source>assertThat(something,or(isNull(),lt(10));
assertThat(something,not(equ("The World"));</source>

				<p>The best part about this is that if the above assertions fail, you'll see 
		    output like:</p>

        <ul><code>AssertionFailedError: Value: 11; Expected: null or less than 10</code><br/>
        <code>AssertionFailedError: Value: "The World"; Expected: not equal to "The World"</code></ul><p/>

				<p>This is in contrast to the standard (none) message, which forces us to write
			  a message for each assertion. This form of usage is well described in an
			  entry on <a href='http://joe.truemesh.com/blog/'>Joe Walnes' Blog</a>, which 
        discusses MockObject's constraints.</p></li>

        <li><p>In situations where you are using several solutions each with their own constraints
        classes, and want to consolidate your custom constraint logic to a single, easy to maintain 
	      implementation, for example to share complex filtering constraints between your 
        MockObjects-based unit tests, and your constraint-based Picocontainer tree.</p></li>
  
      </ul>

      <p>Juno is fairly new, and we are very interested to hear your
      comments, ideas, or to receive your contributions. Please contact us at 
      <a href='mailto:owner@juno.dev.java.net'>owner@juno.dev.java.net</a>.</p>

      <p>Please see the <a href='apidocs/'>Javadoc</a> for usage information.</p>

    </section>

    <section name="Compatibility">
      <p>Juno is compiled for compatibility with JDK 1.3, although it is not tested
      (or supported) below 1.4. We do provide a number of features specific to JSE 5.0
      (a.k.a. 1.5), such as the static import classes, but in all cases these are
      optional extensions and can usually be done without. The static-import syntax
      sugar, for example, allows the sugar definition methods (<code>not</code>, 
      <code>isNull()</code>, and so on) to be easily reused in other classes without
      affecting any existing class hierarchy.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="Download">
      <p>Juno can be downloaded from:</p>

      <ul>
        <li><a href='http://juno.dev.java.net/servlets/ProjectDocumentList'>Milestone &amp; Releases</a></li>
        <li><code>cvs -d:pserver:guest@cvs.dev.java.net:/cvs co juno/main</code></li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section name="Project information">

      <p>Juno is licenced under the usual Roscopeco Open Source licence,
      namely the Apache Software Licence, version 2.0. The full licence terms are
      included <a href="license.html">here</a>.</p>

      <p>Hosting, collaboration and development services are provided by
        <a href="http://www.java.net">Java.net</a>.
      </p>

      <p align="center">
        <a href="http://www.opensource.org" title="OpenSource Initiative approved OSS license" id="osiApproved"><img height="50" width="60" alt="" src="http://opensource.org/trademarks/osi-certified/web/transparent/osi-certified-60x50-t.png"/></a>
        <a href="http://www.java.net" title="Java.net member project" id="javaNet"><img alt="Java.net member project" src="images/javanet_button_90.gif"/></a>
      </p>
    </section>
    
  </body>
</document>
