<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="rosco@[nospam].roscopeco.co.uk">Ross Bamford</author>
    <title>Introduction</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Introduction to Jen">
      <p>Jen is a high-level, lightweight, high-performance Java classworking and bytecode manipulation
      library based on the powerful <a href='http://asm.objectweb.org/'>ASM</a> library, 
      and was written with the aim of providing more pleasant, intuitive development experience than,
      for example, <a href='http://cglib.sf.net/'>Cglib</a>, allowing common use cases to be a
      matter of a few method calls, while retaining the complete control and flexibility that's so
      often the reason to turn to generated classes in the first place. Instead of aiming for ease
      of use by simplification, Jen instead aims to provide a richly layered API that provides 
      sensible defaults for <em>"ninety percent of the options, ninety percent of the time"</em>.
      Jen provides a very short and shallow learning curve for newcomers, and successfully 
      translates that into a carefully-designed ergonomic providing sophisticated utility for
      those with more experience inside the JVM.</p>

      <p>In some respects the Jen core is similar to the 
      <a href='http://www.csg.is.titech.ac.jp/~chiba/javassist/'>Javassist</a> in that it's API revolves
      around the actual members of the class, although it goes far futher in attempting to make the 
      generation transparent where possible, for example by dealing in Java names and <code>java.lang.Class</code>
      instances rather than internal names and type handles. Additionally, Jen provides a far richer
      set of standard implementations, though this is due mainly to Javassist's more pure focus 
      on tooling.</p>

      <subsection name="Project goals">

        <p>Jen aims to deliver the following:</p>
        
        <ul>
          <li><strong>Works the way you do</strong>. Rather than requiring knowledge of the bare internals
          of the JVM, Creating and transforming classes with Jen involves manipulation of high-level objects 
          representing <i>Members</i> - classes, methods, and fields. Standard implementations of these types
          provide for a wide range of common needs - getters and setters, constant fields, null constructors,
          and so on, so many tasks can be achieved by simply plugging in these standard members.
          </li><p/>
          
          <li><strong><code>java.lang.Class</code>-based transformation API</strong>. In Jen, everything 
          revolves around the <i>SoftClass</i>, which can be instantiated with a Java Class to work with
          existing classes, using bytecode from a file or the network, or empty to create a new class.
          </li><p/>
          
          <li><strong>Gain complete control</strong>. Rename classes, modify constant fields, add, remove and
          replace methods and constructors, even copy methods between classes, wrap their invocations,
          or dispatch them dynamically to a (platform-compatible) proxy invocation handler. Jen makes
          it as easy as 1-2-3.
          </li><p/>
          
          <li><strong>A powerful toolkit</strong>. Jen provides a complete classworking toolkit complete with
          all the usual suspects, from proxies to mocks. All the standard tools are built around the same 
          easy-to-use core, placing an amazing amount of power right at your fingertips.
          </li><p/>
          
          <li><strong>Full support for Java 5 features</strong>. Jen fully supports generation of classes
          targeted at any specification version up to and including J5 (and beyond), and includes designed
          in support for new features such as annotations, generics, and autoboxing.
          </li><p/>
          
          <li><strong>Transparent integration</strong>. The <code>SoftClass</code> API is implemented on top
          of ASM alone, and provides support for generation and transformation directly to and from bytecode,
          as well as functioning with standard ASM <code>org.objectweb.asm.ClassVisitor</code>s. Thus, when
          the control offered by the high-level API isn't enough you can still leverage the automatic member
          generation, naming and removal features of Jen as part of your custom visitor chain.
          </li><p/>
        </ul>
      </subsection>
      
      <p>Jen is a lightweight, low dependency library, relying at runtime only on the ASM 2.1 core, commons, 
      attrs and tree libraries, together with <a href='http://roscopeco.co.uk/bloxx/multiproject/juno' target='_blank'>
      Bloxx Juno</a> constraints library if the Jen-Tools mock functionality is used. 
      Thanks to ASM's lightweight, high performance design, and the careful implementation of Jen's
      functionality atop it, the net result is a small, fast library that can slot in almost anywhere.</p>

      <p>Please see the <a href='/multiproject/jen-core/apidocs/index.html'>core</a>, 
      <a href='/multiproject/jen-members/apidocs/index.html'>members</a> and 
      <a href='/multiproject/jen-tools/apidocs/index.html'>tools</a> Javadocs 
      for more detailed usage information. A number of examples can be found on the
      <a href='http://wiki.java.net/bin/view/Javatools/JenSoftClass'>Wiki</a>.</p>

    </section>
  </body>
</document>
